so the quiz we just did shows that
adding more cores might result in a
slowdown if we have to stay within the
same power budget but this is only true
if we cannot adjust the voltage and
frequency so that when there is no
parallelism available we boost the
frequency of the one or two active cores
so that they get the full power budget
of the chip modern processors do this
let's look at an example of intel's core
i7 4702 mq which was released in the
second quarter of 2013. it's a mobile
processor so its design power
is only 37 watts that's what we can call
in a laptop apparently it has four cores
and its normal clock when using all four
cores is 2.2 gigahertz maximum
it can actually save power because it
might operate on a battery by reducing
this frequency even when running
all four cores
but the processor has a turbo frequency
of 3.2 gigahertz
when running only one core that
frequency is
1.45 times the normal frequency
if we assume that the power increases
cubically with this
then we would get 3 times the power
so we are not using 4 times the power
of a single core
which we should be able to get because
it's four cores
so when operating one quarter of the
course
that one quarter of the course can get
four times the power we're only getting
three times so the question is why not
four times
well because it's not only about the
overall chip power what's really
happening is that if we have a
relatively large ship
and we have four cores on it let's say
and we keep heating up this part of the
chip
the heat will spread
into other parts of the chip but this
one will still be hotter than the others
so if we're spending power evenly across
the chip we can spend more power than if
we spend it all in one corner of the
chip
because if we spread the power around
then the chip overall gets hotter
if we spend all power in the same place
then that place gets a lot hotter than
before so that's why three times and not
four times because at three times the
power this part of the chip achieves
similar temperatures
to those achieved
by spreading the heat around at 2.2
gigahertz let's look at another example
which is intel score i7 4771 it's a
similar processor released in third
quarter of 2013 so they're
relatively similar in terms of
technology and so on but this is not a
laptop processor its design power is
much higher at 84 watts
it also has four cores
but the normal clock of a core
is now 3.5 gigahertz much larger than in
the mobile processor
the turbo clock when running only one
core
is 3.9 gigahertz or only
above normal and if we assume that the
power is cubically growing with
frequency that means it's only spending
1.38 times the power of a core when
working with three other cores why is it
like that well because
this being a non-mobile processor has
much better cooling
so it can call the chip when operating
at this high power
but that also means that the chip is
already pretty hot
and getting it even slightly hotter in
any place
very quickly reaches the temperatures at
which it's dangerous for the chip so we
could only really spend this much more
power in one core
even though the others are not working
so pretty much what's happening is
when running at
four cores
the chip is very close to not being able
to cool
if we turbo boost a particular part of
the chip
it gets even hotter
and we can only afford a little bit more
of heat before we run into cooling
issues even though the heat is kind of
leaking to the cooler parts of the chip
it's just not doing it enough and this
is pretty typical that
cores designed for lower power have more
flexibility in shifting that power
whereas if we are near the limits of
what we can do then really shifting the
power
so that it can all be consumed in one
corner very quickly gets that one corner
of the chip to overheat